so hi my name is Joe brewer and I'm a
change strategist and today I want to
share with you a book that will help you
understand a larger pattern in
civilizations as we look at them across
the decades and centuries and that is
the relationship between the structure
of a society and the land use practices
practices or the management of soil as
it pertains to the way that the society
crew how models of ownership arise and
the way that the civilization eventually
either fell and collapsed or was able to
transform itself and be resilient in
times of change in the book that
explores this exceedingly well as this
one dirt the erosion of civilization by
David R Montgomery now David Montgomery
is a soil scientist and he is a
professor have Earth System science at
the University of Washington and what he
does in this book dirt is he looks at
the the data from soil meaning he goes
back and looks at the the soil content
of different layers of dirt below the
ground and then correlates it with
historic events in different regions of
the world so he goes and to a lengthy
discussion of the the different periods
of time for the Roman Empire and how the
plantations were either large or small
and the type of land management
practices that were involved and either
related to the types of economic systems
and political systems that were created
similarly when we look at areas like the
Nile River in northeastern Africa
especially in Egypt where there's been a
civilization for eight thousand ten
thousand years and they've been living
sustainably in that River Delta for all
of that time then what will happen when
we put in a large industrial scale 20th
century Dam as we did in the 1970s and
then we go from a period of 8,000 years
of abundant food production to within 20
years widespread poverty and
malnourishment among the Egyptian people
the Ethiopian people the Eritrean people
who whose livelihoods depend upon the
water and land practices associated with
the Nile River so when we look at these
large-scale patterns of how human
communities use in the land and manage
ownership and production like
agricultural production of the land it
shapes the types of societies that
become possible and this book also goes
into so you can see on the picture here
this is the Dust Bowl in the
southwestern United States in the early
20th century
it also looks at the the rise of slavery
and its relationship to plantations in
the southern United States in its early
history so one thing that I didn't know
until I read this book was that the
economics of slavery only made sense
when the farmers were mostly growing
tobacco crops which are a high market
value yield in a small amount of land
that rapidly depletes the resources of
the land and so actually the cheapest
input into tobacco production and
actually later a cotton production had
this as phenomenon to the cheapest input
was the free quote unquote free labor of
ownership of other people of slavery and
as the the plantation owners would use
up their land and move from place to
place they basically laid the
foundations for the economic collapse
that helped drive the United States into
the Civil War so in a similar way
land-use practices shape the viability
or susceptibility and vulnerability of a
civilization as time goes on so if you
want to better understand how layout
practices and soil management in
particular relates to the dynamics of
civilizations and the viability of
political and economic systems then get
the rider to the erosion of
civilizations by David Montgomery I
think it's a wonderful book and I hope
you enjoy it too